# Rajat Prakash Singh Data Scientist

Phone: +91-8800317147Email: rajat199292@outlook.comLocation: Noida, IndiaGitHub: rajat199292LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/rajatprakashsinghKaggle: singhrajat05

#### PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY:

Data Science, 4+ years of broad-based experience in building data-intensive applications, overcoming complex architectural, and scalability issues in diverse industries, Knowledge in data processing, data mining algorithms, and data predictive modeling with 90% accuracy using scripting language-Python and developing language C#(.NET). Capable of creating, developing, testing, and deploying highly adaptive diverse services to translate business and functional qualifications.

#### SKILLS:

 Technical: Algorithms, Statistics, Data Manipulation and Analysis, Data Visualization, Quantitative Analysis, Predictive Modeling, Classification, Regression, Decision Trees, K-Nearest Neighbors, Decision Trees, Hypothesis Testing, Principal Component Analysis (PCA), Factor Analysis, Model Fitting, Cross-Validation

Language: Data Structure, C++, C#, Python (Sci-kit Learn, Pandas, SciPy, NumPy)

Databases: MS-SQLTools: Tableau, Git

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE:**

#### Hitachi

# **Associate Signal and Functional Engineer**

#### April 2019 - Present

- Increased efficiency for application program designer up to 70 % by performing descriptive analysis of error types by segregating errors into 3 groups depending on the centroid values.
- Drive the interaction and designer between the managers to ensure active cooperation in identifying as well as defining analytical needs and generating the insights for business. Inc. 60% change in business.
- Build predictive models using various machine learning tools to predict the possibility of success of project with 80% accuracy.
- Evaluated of Application Data Design for more than 30 Indian railway stations, across five zones in Train Control Systems as
  per Railway's technical & signaling standards and responsible for verification of Application data in IFAT, CFAT and SAT for
  errors and Analysis, with 80% accuracy rate.

Tool and Tech-Stack: Machine Learning, Python (Sci-kit Learn, Pandas, NumPy), MS-SQL, MS-excel.

## **Ajeevi Technologies**

# **Software Engineer**

May 2018 - March 2019

- Performed individual reports and designed the final and beta dashboards to visualize fleet-related incidents and jobs to meet their requirements. 90% accuracy while performing the ML algorithms.
- Designed and standardized functional enhancements on reporting and analytics utilizing python with ML model and achieved 20% better return in comparison to historical results.
- Develop a user-friendly system for smart fleet management. The module gives measures the bus km, bus performance, store purchases, and stock report. Deployed diverse types of Report using C# and SQL with SSRS Report with 100% scabble.

**Tool and Tech-Stack:** Python, ML, Python (Sci-kit Learn, Pandas, NumPy), MS-SQL, Visual Studio, Tableau **Caddsoft India Pvt. Ltd.** 

# **Software Engineer**

#### Sept 2017 - Dec 2017

- Used ML techniques on python to predict the customer most like food as per restaurants from Republiq app data cleaning by merging multiple datasets treating missing value followed by training the model on a sufficiently large amount of observation.
- Develop a Payment module with Different Payment Gateway Integration with all details required for payment gateway,
   User invite, and Business module with the data-driven dashboard where Merchant can see their daily report. S2S affiliate marketing In Republiq.
- Actively engaged in the quantitative analysis of sophisticated modelling to address business issues that have improved business by 30%.

Tool and Tech-Stack: ML, Python, MS-SQL, Visual Studio, ASP.NET

# Ajeevi Technologies

# Software Engineer

# June 2016 - Aug 2017

- Coded a user-friendly system for Fleet management and different type of stored procedures and implementation of LINQ and provide analysis fleet dashboard and system efficiency inc. by 70%.
- Maintained and test several types of stored procedures for uses dashboard and built API that helps fetching data for apps show 95% accurate GPS data.

Tool and Tech-Stack: Python, MS-SQL, Visual Studio, ASP.NET

## **PROJECT**

## **Understanding Customers' Buying Patterns for an Automobile Parts Manufacturer**

This project aims to find the underlying buying patterns of the customers of an automobile part manufacturer based on the
past 3 years of the Company's transaction data and hence recommend customized marketing strategies for different
segments of customers.

Tool and Tech-Stack: Python, MS-SQL, RFM, Exploratory Data Analysis, KNIME

#### **Visualizing Insurance Claims**

• This project explored the art of problem-solving with the aid of visual analytics. Tableau's data visualization tools were used to create interactive dashboards to provide high-level insights FOR policymaking.

Tool and Tech-Stack: Python, MS-SQL, Exploratory Data Analysis, Business Intelligence, Tableau, Dashboard Designing

## **Election Exit Poll Prediction and U.S.A Presidential Speech Analysis**

• predict which party a citizen is going to vote for on the basis of their age and according to the answers given by the citizens to the questions asked in a survey conducted.

**Tool and Tech-Stack:** Python, MS-SQL, Exploratory Data Analysis, Business Intelligence, K Nearest, Naive Bayes, Ensemble Techniques, Logistic Regression, Linear Discriminant Analysis

## **Gems & Holiday Package Prediction**

- Gems Price Prediction and Holiday Package prediction. In the first case study, concepts of linear regression are tested and it is expected from the learner to predict the price of gems based on multiple variables to help company maximize profits
- One has to predict if the customer will purchase the holiday package to target the relevant customer base.

**Tool and Tech-Stack:** Python, MS-SQL, Exploratory Data Analysis, Business Intelligence, Ensemble Techniques, Linear Regression, Logistic Regression, Linear discriminant Analysis

#### **EDUCATION**

## **Great Lakes Executive Learning, Gurugram**

May 2021 - May 2022

Post Graduate in Data Science and Business Analytics

## Dr. A.P.J. Abdul Kalam Technical University, Uttar Pradesh

May 2012 - May 2016

Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science

## LICENSES AND CERTIFICATIONS

- Certificate in Machine Learning in R by Collabera TACT with 80% marks.
- MTA in Software Fundamentals C# and MTA in Database Fundamentals with 90% marks.

#### **ACHIEVEMEN**

- Selected as Microsoft Student Partner and Microsoft Student Associate among 10k student.
- Selected as Best Paper award for "Content based Image retrieval" in 11th National Conference on Next Generation Technologies.